If nothing else, it's a story that we would've needed to hear when we were younger. Given the nature of our story, I know the words that inevitably accompany it -- victim, rapist -- and labels are a way to organize concepts, but they can also be dehumanizing in their connotations. Once someone's been deemed a victim, it's that much easier to file them away as someone damaged, dishonored, less than. And likewise, once someone has been branded a rapist, it's that much easier to call him a monster -- inhuman. But how will we understand what it is in human societies that produces violence if we refuse to recognize the humanity of those who commit it? And how -- (Applause) And how can we empower survivors if we're making them feel less than? How can we discuss solutions to one of the biggest threats to the lives of women and children around the world, if the very words we use are part of the problem? TS: From what I've now learnt, my actions that night in 1996 were a self-centered taking. I felt deserving of Thordis's body. I've had primarily positive social influences and examples of equitable behavior around me. But on that occasion, I chose to draw upon the negative ones. The ones that see women as having less intrinsic worth, and of men having some unspoken and symbolic claim to their bodies. These influences I speak of are external to me, though. And it was only me in that room making choices, nobody else. When you own something and really square up to your culpability, I do think a surprising thing can happen. It's what I call a paradox of ownership. I thought I'd buckle under the weight of responsibility. I thought my certificate of humanity would be burnt. Instead, I was offered to really own what I did, and found that it didn't possess the entirety of who I am. Put simply, something you've done doesn't have to constitute the sum of who you are. The noise in my head abated. The indulgent self-pity was starved of oxygen, and it was replaced with the clean air of acceptance -- an acceptance that I did hurt this wonderful person standing next to me; an acceptance that I am part of a large and shockingly everyday grouping of men who have been sexually violent toward their partners. Don't underestimate the power of words. Saying to Thordis that I raped her changed my accord with myself, as well as with her. But most importantly, the blame transferred from Thordis to me. Far too often, the responsibility is attributed to female survivors of sexual violence, and not to the males who enact it. Far too often, the denial and running leaves all parties at a great distance from the truth. There's definitely a public conversation happening now, and like a lot of people, we're heartened that there's less retreating from this difficult but important discussion. I feel a real responsibility to add our voices to it. TE: What we did is not a formula that we're prescribing for others. Nobody has the right to tell anyone else how to handle their deepest pain or their greatest error. Breaking your silence is never easy, and depending on where you are in the world, it can even be deadly to speak out about rape. I realize that even the most traumatic event of my life is still a testament to my privilege, because I can talk about it without getting ostracized, or even killed. But with that privilege of having a voice comes the responsibility of using it. That's the least I owe my fellow survivors who can't. The story we've just relayed is unique, and yet it is so common with sexual violence being a global pandemic. But it doesn't have to be that way. One of the things that I found useful on my own healing journey is educating myself about sexual violence. And as a result, I've been reading, writing and speaking about this issue for over a decade now, going to conferences around the world. And in my experience, the attendees of such events are almost exclusively women. But it's about time that we stop treating sexual violence as a women's issue. (Applause) A majority of sexual violence against women and men is perpetrated by men. And yet their voices are sorely underrepresented in this discussion. But all of us are needed here. Just imagine all the suffering we could alleviate if we dared to face this issue together. Thank you. (Applause)
Más que esto, es una historia que necesitábamos escuchar cuando éramos más jóvenes. Dada la naturaleza de nuestra historia, conozco las palabras que la acompañan -- víctima, violador -- y las etiquetas son maneras de organizar conceptos, pero también pueden ser deshumanizantes en sus connotaciones. Cuando alguien se convierte en víctima, es muy fácil catalogarla como dañada, deshonrada, menos que eso. De la misma forma, cuando a alguien se le etiqueta como violador, es muy fácil llamarle monstruo -- inhumano. ¿Pero cómo podemos entender qué es lo que en la sociedad causa violencia si nos negamos a reconocer la humanidad de quien lo comete? (Aplausos) ¿Cómo empoderar a los sobrevivientes si los hacemos sentir menos? ¿Cómo discutir soluciones para una de las mayores amenazas en la vida de las mujeres y niños en el mundo, si las palabras que usamos son parte del problema? TS: Aprendí, que mis acciones aquella noche de 1996 fueron egocéntricas. Sentí merecer el cuerpo de Thordis. Tuve influencias sociales positivas y ejemplos de similar conducta a mi alrededor. Pero en aquella ocasión, escogí las influencias negativas. Las que dicen que las mujeres tienen un valor menor, y que los hombres tienen cierto poder sobre los cuerpos de ellas. Sin embargo, estas influencias son externas a mí. Solamente fui yo en ese cuarto el que tomó las decisiones, nadie más. Cuando te apropias de algo y reconoces tu culpa, creo que algo sorprendente puede pasar. Es lo que llamo la paradoja de la apropiación. Pensé que me doblaría bajo el peso de la responsabilidad. Que mi certificado de humanidad sería quemado. En vez, tuve la oportunidad de apropiarme de lo que hice, me di cuenta de que aquello no representaba todo lo que yo soy. En pocas palabras, algo que hiciste no tiene que constituir la suma de lo que eres. El ruido en mi cabeza disminuyó. La autocompasión tenía hambre de oxígeno, y fue reemplazada con el limpio aire de la aceptación -- la aceptación de que le hice daño a esta increíble persona a mi lado; la aceptación de que soy parte de un grupo de hombres que crece cada día los cuales han sido sexualmente violentos con sus parejas. No subestimen el poder de las palabras. Decirle a Thordis que la violé cambió mi armonía conmigo mismo, y también con ella. Más importante que esto, la culpa se transfirió de Thordis a mí. Muy a menudo, la responsabilidad se le atribuye a las sobrevivientes de la violencia sexual, y no a los hombres que la cometen. Muy a menudo, negar y huir aleja a todos de la realidad. Definitivamente hay un diálogo público ocurriendo en este momento y, como a mucha gente, nos conmueve que haya menos rechazo de esta difícil pero importante discusión. Siento una real responsabilidad de contribuir con nuestras voces. TE: Lo que hicimos no es una fórmula que le prescribamos a otros. Nadie tiene el derecho de decirle a alguien cómo manejar su dolor o sus mayores errores. Romper con el silencio nunca es fácil, y dependiendo de dónde estés en el mundo, puede ser mortal hablar sobre violación. Sé que hasta el más traumático evento de mi vida es un testamento de mi privilegio, pues puedo hablar sobre él sin ser condenada al ostracismo, o ser asesinada. Pero con el privilegio de tener una voz viene la responsabilidad de usarla. Es lo que le debo a las sobrevivientes que no pueden. La historia que contamos es única, pero tan común siendo la violencia sexual una pandemia global. Pero no tiene que ser así. Algo que resultó ser útil en mi proprio viaje de curación es educarme sobre la violencia sexual. Como resultado, he leído, he escrito y charlado sobre este problema por más de una década, participando en conferencias alrededor del mundo. En mi experiencia, los que asisten a esos eventos son casi exclusivamente mujeres. Es tiempo de que dejemos de tratar la violencia sexual como un problema femenino. (Aplausos) La mayoría de la violencia sexual contra las mujeres y los hombres es realizadas por hombres. Y aun sus voces están poco representadas en esta discusión. Se necesita que todos estemos aquí. Imaginen todo el sufrimiento que podríamos aliviar si nos atreviéramos a enfrentar esto juntos. Gracias. (Aplausos)